第四集：鱼类
我们的地球是颗蓝色的行星
Ours is truly a blue planet.
水覆盖了大部分地球表面
Water covers most of the world's surface.
在这里我们是旁观者
Here we are the outsiders.
但碧波之下，有种生物却很兴盛
But under the waves one group thrives.
鱼类是水中高手
Fish are masters of the waters.
旗鱼又是所有鱼中最快的
And sailfish are the fastest of them all.
速度使它们成为海洋里最可怕的食肉动物之一
Their speed makes them one of the ocean's most fearsome predators.
墨西哥海域，30条旗鱼包围着一群沙丁鱼
Off the coast of Mexico, 30 sailfish have surrounded a ball of sardines.
要抓到猎物，不仅仅单靠速度
To catch their prey requires more than speed alone.
急转弯时，鱼鳍依旧结实
In the tightest turns, fins maintain stability.
它们靠镰刀形的尾巴驱动前进
Their sickle-shaped tail powers them forwards
外形奇特的背鳍能够恐吓猎物
and that extraordinary dorsal fin helps intimidate their prey.
肉眼看来，它们的动作太快了
To the naked eye, the action is too fast,
慢镜头下，它们的战术才清晰呈现
slowed, their challenge becomes clear.
选定一个目标非常困难
Just picking a target is hard enough.
通过敲打使它失去平衡，并将之从鱼群里孤立出来
Knocking it off balance, separates it from the shoal.
这需要极高的技巧
This requires extraordinary skill.
并非每次尝试都能成功
Not every attempt is successful.
但随着越来越多的旗鱼加入，一个失手，另一个迅速跟上
But as more sailfish join in, when one misses another takes its place.
这群沙丁鱼被有条不紊地猎食殆尽
The shoal of sardines is methodically wiped out.
旗鱼是顶级猎食者，极少生物能威胁到它们
Sailfish are top predators, very little threatens them.
对大多数的鱼类来说，不是这回事
But for the majority of fish this is not the case.
开阔的海洋对它们是极度危险的
For most fish the open ocean is extremely dangerous.
有些能作出惊人之举，只为逃生
And some go to extraordinary lengths just to survive.
飞鱼
Flying fish.
靠超长的鳍，它们飞出水面
Free of the water they soar on elongated fins,
将猎食者远远甩在后面
leaving their predators far behind.
鱼类的飞行家
A flight of fish.
飞鱼所面临的考验，不仅仅只是逃避天敌
Escaping predators is not the only test facing the flying fish.
它们也必须保护发育中的后代
They must also protect their developing young.
飞鱼在寻找一种特殊的东西，使之成为可能
These flying fish are searching for the one thing that will make this possible.
在如此辽阔的海洋里，并不容易
In such a vast ocean it's not easy.
它们很幸运
They're in luck.
一片棕榈叶
A palm frond.
海洋里漂流的微型岛屿
It's a tiny island adrift in a huge ocean.
它可以提供庇护所，但不是为飞鱼
And like an island it offers shelter, not for the flying fish,
而是给它们的卵
but for their eggs.
雌鱼在叶子上产卵，雄鱼使它们受精
The females lay eggs on the raft, where the males fertilise them.
一条鱼的排卵会引发其它的鱼也开始排卵
The first fish spawn and this triggers the others to start.
不一会儿，成千上万条鱼参与进来
Soon thousands join the melee.
产下难以计数的卵
Innumerable strands of eggs are laid.
重压之下“木筏”开始倾斜
The raft starts to tilt under their weight.
最佳产卵地点在叶子的中间
The best place to lay eggs is right inside the frond.
有些尝试被证明是失败的，它成了一些鱼的坟墓
For some the attempt proves fatal and living fish become entombed.
在如此多鱼卵的重压下，它开始下沉
The raft starts to sink under the weight of so many eggs.
但这并非灾难
But this is far from a disaster.
沉到水面以下，实际上可以提高鱼卵的存活机会
Sinking away from the surface actually improves the eggs' chances of survival.
在深处安全地躲避着，几天后
In just a few days, having been safely hidden in the depths,
它们全都孵化出来
they'll hatch out.
其它的鱼则用不同的方式保护后代
Other fish protect their offspring in different ways.
有些在照料后代方面走的更远
Some go to far greater lengths to care for them.
澳大利亚南部的浅水区
The shallow waters of southern Australia
是许多奇异生物的家园
are home to many strange creatures.
童话般的海马王国
It's a fairytale world of sea horses...
占星鱼（一直瞪着眼看天空）
..stargazers...
鳐鱼
..and stingrays.
但谁也比不上海藻龙的美丽
But none compare with the beauty of the weedy sea dragon.
它的背鳍快速地震动
The dragon's tiny fins beat frantically
防止自己被水流冲走
to prevent the current from sweeping it away.
现在是早春
It's the beginning of spring,
海藻龙的求爱期开始了
the season when sea dragons begin their courtship.
在夜光下，它们开始跳舞
And in the evening light, they start to dance.
在优美的二重奏里，一只龙能准确地模仿伴侣的动作
In a graceful duet, each partner mirrors the actions of the other.
夜色很快就将这一对儿笼罩
Darkness will soon draw a veil over the pair
但它们会继续跳舞，直到深夜
but they will dance on, into the night.
两个月后，它们的爱情结晶就会出现
Two months later, and the result of their courtship is revealed.
雄性海藻龙，它是携带着卵的那只
It's the male and he's the one that's carrying the eggs,
一排一排的固定在它的尾巴上
with rows and rows of them embedded in his tail.
那一夜，雌性将卵移交给了它
That night the female transferred her eggs to him.
从那以后，它将独自照看这些卵
Since then, the male alone has cared for them.
这样随身带着它们可以保证安全
By carrying them with him he's kept them safe.
现在，是它的付出得到回报的时候了
And now it's time for his efforts to be rewarded.
卵开始孵化
The eggs are ready to hatch.
在一个宁静的夏日早晨
In the calm of a summer morning
一个还带着卵囊小海龙诞生了
a baby sea dragon, with yolk sac still attached, is born.
海藻床为能够自己觅食的
The weed bed shelters older dragons
成年海龙提供庇护
that are already able to feed themselves.
尽管这些小海龙从父亲那里得到了很好的照料
Although these dragons were well cared for by their father,
如今，它们必须独自寻找食物
now they must find their own way in the world.
然而，还有一种鱼
There are fish, however,
能够给后代提供更为长久的保护
which provide their young with a safe refuge for far longer.
太平洋西南部
The south western Pacific.
喷沙鱼（译者自命名）
A convict fish
它是海底的建筑师
and it's something of a marine architect.
在地下制造了迷宫一样的通道
Underground it has created a labyrinth of tunnels.
成年鱼从来不敢从洞里出来，它吃什么仍旧是个谜
This adult never ventures out of its burrow, what it eats is a mystery.
但它并非独住
But it doesn't live here alone.
另一个门口露出了许多小脸儿
At another entrance faces peer out.
幼年喷沙鱼
Juvenile convict fish.
不像成年鱼，这些小子不会被地洞所束缚
Unlike their parent, the youngsters are not tied to the burrow.
一旦它们现身，细流会变成洪水
And as they start to emerge, a trickle becomes a flood of fish.
成千上万
There are thousands of them.
它们都帮助做家务
And they all help with the chores.
鱼多力量大
Many hands make light work.
它们在一起游动
The young fish swarm together.
上万张嘴吞食食物
Thousands of mouths gulping plankton.
成年鱼吃什么，应该跟这些小鱼有关
What the adults eat must somehow involve these youngsters.
到底是小鱼们通过反刍来喂养大鱼呢？
Whether the young feed their parents by regurgitating food
还是有其它的方式，我们无从得知
or through some other mechanism, we just don't know.
无论答案如何，小鱼们给大鱼提供食物
Whatever the answer, the youngsters provide
它们的父母则提供庇护所作为回报
their parents with a meal and in return get a roof over their heads.
繁衍后代只是一个挑战
Producing young is just one challenge.
寻找食物和居住场所，是鱼类必须面临的进一步考验
Finding food and somewhere to live are further trials fish must face.
加利福利亚海岸，生存着大量的生物
The Californian coast, a wide range of species live here.
这也意味着生存空间的竞争异常激烈
But all this life means competition for living space is intense.
老掉的贝壳是很宝贵的
Old shells are highly prized.
这个壳被一个怪头鱼（译者自命名）所占据
And this one is occupied by a sarcastic fringehead.
这种鱼非常的好斗
These fish are exceptionally quarrelsome,
它们必须保护自己的住所
they have to be, to defend their living space.
一条章鱼
An octopus.
一不小心就进入了怪头鱼的地盘
Inadvertently it's wandered into the fringehead's territory
这是无法容忍的
and that can't be tolerated.
章鱼用特殊的腕足猛戳怪头鱼
The octopus's impressive jab holds the fringehead at bay.
这种行为远非坏脾气所能解释
There is more to this behaviour than being bad-tempered.
想要得到充足的食物，怪头鱼必须守住自己的场子
The fringehead needs to defend its patch if it is to get enough to eat
章鱼就是个对手
and the octopus was competition.
蟹可不是那么好吞的
Crabs are not the easiest of mouthfuls.
由于生存空间狭小，这里总有不间断的领土纠纷
Because of the shortage of living space there are constant boundary disputes,
特别是和另一条怪头鱼
especially with other fringeheads
这家伙越界了
and this one has got too close.
尽管面对如此夸张的恐吓
Despite the most extravagant threats...
它们都不打算收手
..neither is prepared to back down.
胜利了，然后迅速回到壳里
Success, and it's quick to get back to its shell.
怪头鱼从来不会放松警惕，因为竞争者实在太多
A fringehead can never drop its guard, there's too much competition.
有些鱼类则迁移到竞争相对较少的地方
Some fish have moved to places where they have fewer rivals.
弹涂鱼，一生中大部分时间都在水外度过
A mudskipper a fish that spends most of its life out of the sea.
它能在地上爬行，呼吸空气
It can walk on land and breathe air.
生活方式和大部分的鱼很不相同
Its life is very different from that of most fish.
一般的鱼偶尔也会出水
A fish out of water maybe,
但它们在日本的这个地方却很繁盛
but they thrive here in Japan.
所以，为何作出如此大的改变？
So what's made this upheaval worthwhile?
答案就在泥巴里
The answer lies in the mud.
退潮后，暴露出一片滩涂
As the tide retreats it exposes mudflats.
阳光照耀在肥沃的泥土上，各种小型生物得以繁盛
Sunlight hits the rich silt and tiny plants and animals flourish there.
这些都是弹涂鱼的食物
All food for a mudskipper.
但陆上生活并非没有麻烦
But life on land is not without problems,
很难找到配偶
it's hard work to find a mate.
从泥滩上高高跃起，可以让自己受到关注
Jumping high above the mud will get you noticed.
弹涂鱼那双长在头顶的双眼
With eyes perched on top of their heads
时刻关注着朋友，警惕着敌人
the mudskippers keep a look out for both friend and foe.
雄性还会同入侵者打斗
And males fight those who intrude on their territory.
它们也要谨防自己被晒干
They must also take care not to dry out in the sun.
在泥浆里打滚能够降温并且保湿
Rolling in the ooze keeps the skin cool and moist.
对这种小动物来说
For this smaller species,
退回地下乃是上策
a better option is to retreat underground.
所以它在泥巴里为自己挖好了地道
So he digs himself a tunnel down into the mud.
它洞外堆积的泥巴能显示出挖掘的深度
His heap of spoil is an indication of the extent of his excavations.
潮水会每天两次淹没地道
With the tide flooding the tunnel twice a day,
维修工作比较繁重
maintenance is a real burden.
地道不仅仅是躲避太阳的
The tunnel is more than a refuge from the sun,
也有另一种重要的用途
it serves another very important purpose.
地道实际上是U型的，末端有个封闭的小室
The tunnel is actually U-shaped and at the far end is a sealed chamber,
墙壁上布满了鱼卵
the walls of which are lined with eggs.
鱼卵保持露天状态，因为空气中的氧气含量比水中要高
The eggs are kept in air as it's richer in oxygen than the water.
问题是这里所储存的空气支持不了多久
The problem is the air that's trapped here won't last for long.
所以雄鱼会游到洞口，吞下新鲜空气
So the male travels to the open end of the tunnel to gulp fresh air.
再潜回地道将空气吐到孵卵小室里
Back he goes down his tunnel where he releases it into the egg chamber.
补充卵孵化所需的氧气
Replenishing the oxygen on which the eggs depend.
它会一次又一次地重复这个过程，直到后代孵化出来
He will repeat this hundreds and hundreds of times until his young hatch.
尽管这种生活方式很辛苦
This lifestyle is very demanding,
弹涂鱼还是能设法解决每一个问题
yet the mudskipper has found a way around every problem.
海洋里严酷的生活挑战
The harsh challenges of life in the ocean
也迫使另一种鱼离开了大海
have encouraged other fish to leave the sea.
不是去到陆地，而是淡水
Not for land, but for fresh water.
夏威夷是地球上最偏远的群岛
Hawaii is the remotest island chain on the planet.
这溪流看起来是个鱼类生存的好地方
These pools look the perfect place for a fish to live,
独立，没什么竞争和猎食者
secluded and free from competition and predators.
但这里很少有鱼，一个很大的原因是
Yet few contain fish, for one very considerable reason.
没有鱼能上游到这里来
Surely no fish could swim up this.
但有一种来自海洋的鱼，下决心要移民到这条溪流
But one fish comes from the ocean, intent on colonising these streams.
小虾虎鱼，攀岩高手
It's a tiny goby and it's a rock climber.
它的腹鳍呈盘状，像个吸盘
With pelvic fins fused into a disc, which acts like a sucker,
小虾虎鱼只需爬过一层薄的“水墙”
all the goby needs is a film of water to climb through.
先锋不一会儿就被其它的追随
The pioneer is soon followed by many others,
可能是沿着它的气味
possibly following its scent trail.
它们逆着水流向上爬行
They clamber on, ever upwards against the flow.
水滴下来如同炸弹
Drops of water fall like bombs.
失误会导致体力的浪费
False leads waste crucial energy.
有些需要休息
Some must rest.
另一些，消耗太多
For others, the effort is just too much.
会在半路上死掉
Many die in their attempt to reach to top.
尽管困难重重，还是有少数能英雄般地到达上面
Against all the odds a few heroic individuals do make it to the top.
它们为自己找到了一个近乎完美的栖息地
They find themselves in a near-perfect fish habitat...
在那儿，小虾虎鱼能够安宁地生长、繁衍
..where the gobies can feed and grow and breed in peace.
最后，它们的后代会被水流冲走，到达大海
In time their own young will be swept downstream and out to sea
然后开始新一轮的循环
and the cycle will begin all over again.
淡水给鱼类带来了特殊的挑战
Fresh water presents particular challenges for fish.
春天的淡水中，营养非常稀少
Nutrients can be in very short supply in spring water,
所以要找到食物，必须把握住每一个机会
so here fish must take every chance they can to find food.
雨水落到肯尼亚山上，从岩石中渗出来
The rain that falls on these Kenyan hills percolates through the rocks.
最终形成一个个清澈的水池
Finally emerging as crystal clear pools.
是很多鱼类的家，包括鱼
Pools that are home to fish including barbel.
鱼和很多其它的生物在此共存
The fish share these waters with all sorts of creatures...
包括河马
..including hippopotamus.
这些巨大的素食者对鱼类没有威胁
These giant vegetarians are no threat to the fish,
事实上，它们是鱼儿在此生存的关键
in fact they're key to their survival here.
河马们经过陆地上一夜的饱餐
After a night of grazing on land, these hippos return
返回到凉爽的水塘里呆上几小时
to spend the daylight hours in the cooling waters.
鱼们前来迎接
And the barbel come to meet them.
每头河马身后一下子就跟来一群鱼
Soon each hippo is trailed by a shoal of fish,
等待着开饭呢
waiting for their breakfast.
河马排便
Hippo droppings.
但鱼对河马的粪便并不感兴趣
But it's not just the hippo's dung the fish are interested in.
当河马来到水池里合适的地点后
When the hippos reach one particular spot in the pool,
它们便站着不动，等待
they stand still and wait.
鱼们开始清除它们身上的
And the fish start to clean them...
虱子、寄生虫以及可口的碎屑
..removing ticks, parasites and other tasty morsels.
对鱼来说，河马就像是个移动餐厅
To the fish the hippos are a mobile cafeteria.
河马们看起来很享受呢
The hippos seem to be enjoying the sensation.
唯一能打断这场宴会的
The only thing that interrupts the feast
是河马必须浮出水面呼吸
is the need to take an occasional breath.
给河马清洁皮肤只是开胃菜
Cleaning the hippo's skin was just the hors d'oeuvre.
现在到了正餐环节
Now it's time for the main course.
所以，除了帮助治疗皮肤病
So, in addition to providing skin care,
鱼还是河马的口腔医生
the fish look after the hippos' dental hygiene.
这种方式对双方都有利
It's an arrangement that suits both parties.
但有可能鱼们获利更多
But perhaps it is the fish that are the overall winners.
因为，在河马的帮助下
For, thanks to the hippos, they are able to feed on
它们能吃到那些本来遥不可及的
the abundant vegetation that would otherwise be beyond their reach,
生长在水池旁边陆地上的东西
growing around their pool, on land.
很明显，提供清洁服务是混口饭吃的好办法
Providing a cleaning service is clearly a good way of getting a meal.
在海洋里，也有时需要清理服务
And there is cleaning to be done in the sea as well.
这种濑鱼的生活主要集中于清除其它鱼身上的寄生虫
The life of this wrasse is centred on removing parasites from other reef fish...
包括"食肉杰克"（译者自命名）
..including predatory jacks.
通常他们能一口吞下这样的小鱼
Normally they would snap up such a little fish,
但它们有明确的关系
but this is an established relationship
双方都明白游戏规则
and both sides know the rules.
由于食肉杰克太多，而濑鱼很少
With so many jacks and only a few wrasse in attendance,
并非所有的都能得到清理
not all the jacks are going to get cleaned.
这里的生物也引来了其它猎食者
But all this life attracts other predators.
银鲨
Silvertip sharks.
珊瑚礁能给小鱼提供庇护
The reef provides shelter for the smaller fish,
食肉杰克依然暴露
but the jacks remain exposed.
这样或许有了机会
Yet this may be a chance
食肉杰克们可以解决清理问题
for the jacks to solve their cleaning problem.
T它们觅得时机
They've spotted an opportunity.
银鲨的皮肤就像砂纸
Sharks have skin like sand paper.
从鲨鱼的侧边撞过去
And bumping into the sharks' flanks
能够帮助食肉杰克清除掉身上的寄生虫和死皮
helps the jacks to rid themselves of parasites and dead skin.
也许它们发现这种清洁方法比濑鱼还要有效
Perhaps the jacks find this a more effective alternative to the cleaner fish.
不久就有一群食肉杰克尾随着鲨鱼
And soon swarms of jacks pursue the sharks.
都跑过来蹭几下痒痒
All itching to have a scratch.
这种行为无疑让鲨鱼很烦恼
Unsurprisingly all this attention bothers the sharks
它们掉头游向深水区
and they head back to the blue water,
使得珊瑚礁居民的生活回复了宁静
leaving the residents of the reef to resume life as normal.
珊瑚礁是地球上最富饶的生物栖息地
Coral reefs are the richest habitats on Earth.
毫不意外的是
It's not surprising that,
这么多种不同动物紧密地生活在一起
with so many different kinds of animals living so closely together,
必然会演化出一些特殊的种间关系
some extraordinary relationships have evolved.
小丑鱼，没有自卫能力的珊瑚礁居民
A clownfish, a small and defenceless resident of the reef.
看起来选了个糟糕的生活场所
It seems to have picked a tough place to live,
在海葵的触手之间
amongst the tentacles of a sea anemone.
每支触手都有毒刺，可以杀死一条鱼
Each tentacle is armed with paralysing stings that can kill a fish.
但小丑鱼完全不受影响
Yet the clown fish are totally immune.
这一组合，海葵就像城堡
For this pair, the anemone is like a castle.
只要它们呆在海葵周围，就很安全
So long as they stay surrounded by the tentacles, they're safe
它们也在这里产卵
and so this is where they choose to lay their eggs.
经过仔细的地点选择
After carefully selecting the site,
它们开始清扫表面
work begins on preparing the surface.
两条鱼分担工作
Both fish share in the labour,
然后由较大的雄鱼决定是否就绪
though it's the larger female who decides when all is ready.
一行行的小鱼卵被黏附在岩石上，然后受精
Lines and lines of tiny eggs are stuck to the rock and then fertilised.
这些卵很靠近海葵，所以比较安全
They're laid so close to the anemone they will be safe.
接下来的七天，它们会得到始终如一的照顾
And for the next seven days they'll receive constant care...
大部分来自鱼爸爸
..much of which is provided by the male.
它看起来如此担心那些卵，是有原因的
His seemingly obsessive concern for the eggs is for good reason.
鱼卵在海葵丛中并不十分安全
His position in the anemone is far from secure.
雌鱼关注着它的一举一动
The female watches his every move,
她掌控着这里，如果雄鱼的努力不符合她的要求
she's in charge here and if his efforts don't match up
她就会赶走他
to her standards, she'll get rid of him.
排队候补的是一群半大的小丑鱼
In line to take over are a host of immature clown fish...
每一个都伺机取而代之
..each waiting to move up the hierarchy.
对雄鱼来说，得到雌鱼偏爱的最好方法
For the male the best way to stay in the female's favour
就是好好照顾鱼卵
is by lavishing care on the eggs.
所以它集中精力，使它们保持清洁、健康
So he focuses all his efforts on keeping them clean and healthy.
卵发育很快，不久就能看见它们跳动的小心脏
The eggs grow rapidly and soon their tiny beating hearts are visible.
看起来它干得不错
It seems he's done a good job.
小丑鱼可以躲进海葵里休息了
Clown fish can hide away within an anemone.
但大多数的鱼没这个办法
But most fish don't have this option.
有一些，它们逃离危险的唯一途径
For some, the only way of avoiding danger
就是躲进一大群
is by hiding amongst their own kind...
同类中
..in shoals.
尽管很挤，但没一条凤尾鱼跑出来
Packed close together, no one anchovy stands out.
通过感官对同伴的行动做出迅速反应
By sensing and reacting to the movements
它们可以做到“千鱼一律”
of their immediate neighbours, thousands can move as one.
对捕食者来说，从中挑出一条，几乎是不可能的
For a predator, picking out an individual becomes nearly impossible.
团结就是力量
The shoal's unity is its strength.
尽管每条鱼的动机都是利己的
Yet each fish is acting from selfish motives.
通过整体行动，鱼群使得海狮如此迷惑
Moving together, the fish confuse the sea lions so much
它们只得离开，去别处寻找小的、不这么狡猾的目标
that they leave to look elsewhere for a smaller, less tricky target.
鱼群整体击败了海狮
The sheer size of the shoal defeated the sea lions,
但有的鱼可以挫败这种战术
but there are fish that can overcome such strategies.
南非海域
Off the coast of South Africa
这群沙丁鱼被一条锯齿鲨尾随
this huge shoal of sardines is shadowed by a ragged tooth shark.
其它鲨鱼也加入了“护航”
Other sharks join the menacing escort.
这群鱼被一股冷流逼进了浅水区
The shoal has been driven into the shallows by a cold ocean current.
这就给了鲨鱼们机会
And this gives the sharks an opportunity.
几百条鲨鱼就位
Hundreds have moved into position.
鲨鱼有特殊的感官，能侦测出
Sharks have a special sense, they can detect
猎物移动时发出的电信号
the electrical signals their prey gives off when it moves.
这就是使它们占优势的第六感
It's a sixth sense that can give them an edge.
但现在成千上万条鱼挤在浅水区
But with hundreds of thousands of fish crammed into the shallows,
鲨鱼就只能依靠自己的速度和敏捷
the sharks now need only rely on their speed and agility.
一旦第一条鲨鱼开始认真捕猎
As the first shark starts to hunt in earnest,
一场狂乱的盛宴爆发了
a feeding frenzy breaks out.
鱼群的防线开始削弱
The shoal's defences are weakened,
这里没有足够的空间来迂回
there isn't enough space to manoeuvre.
鲨鱼可以吞下它们
And the sharks can gorge themselves.
尽管伤亡很多
Despite the casualties,
但鱼群太过庞大，鲨鱼造成的影响其实非常微小
the shoal is so vast that the sharks have little effect on its size.
鱼类不仅以群体方式进行防御
Fish not only come together in great shoals for defence,
还会在生命中的另一些关键时刻
but at other critical times in their lives,
比如它们排卵
when they're ready to spawn.
这事情只会发生在每年的那几天
These events only occur for a few days each year.
真鳍蓝雕通常独立生活，但它们从伯利兹城海岸
Snapper are normally solitary, but they've travelled here
远道而来，聚集在一起
from hundreds of miles away to gather off the coast of Belize.
沿着这块礁石，真鳍蓝雕形成一个巨大的群体
Along this one reef, cubera, dog and mutton snapper form huge shoals.
60米水下，有着阴森、冰冷的感觉
60 metres down, there is an eerie coolness to the scene.
但马上就要热闹起来
But things are about to hot up.
月圆之夜，潮水刚好
It's the evening of the full moon, the tides are just right.
一大群鱼从海底蹿升
A great column of fish leaves the bottom.
上升途中，一小部分从鱼群中冲出
As they rise through the water, small groups break free of the shoal.
雌鱼在前排卵，雄鱼在后面紧追
Each burst is led by a female, with the males racing behind.
排出卵后，雄鱼将精子与之混合
As she sheds her eggs, they add their sperm to the mix.
由于它们聚集时已同期发情
By synchronising the time when they gather together,
产卵时，参与的鱼能够达到最大数量
the maximum numbers of fish can join in this mass spawning.
数百万的受精卵被释放
Millions of fertilized eggs are released,
汇入了洋流
cast into the ocean currents...
直接进入危险的世界
..and straight into a dangerous world.
鲸鲨，地球上最大的鱼
Whale sharks, the largest fish on Earth.
每一条鲸鲨可重达10吨
Each shark might weigh ten tonnes
但它们却吃极为微小的生物，如真鳍蓝雕的卵
yet they feed on the tiniest creatures, including snapper eggs.
生命的被创造、延续、被消灭
Life is being created, sustained and destroyed simultaneously
在一次大事件里同时发生
in one huge event.
生存斗争，全都浓缩在了这一时刻
The struggle for life, encapsulated into a single moment.
海洋是危险的生存之地
The oceans are perilous places to live,
鱼类已进化出非常特殊的方法以求生存
yet fish have developed the most extraordinary means for survival.
它们惊人的多样性，亿万年的进化成果
Their astounding diversity, the product of millions of years
使它们获得成功
of evolution, has enabled them to triumph.
统治着目前我们自己还无法占据的栖息地
Dominating the one habitat that we have so far failed to make our own.
水下拍摄给Life制作组带来了各种各样的困难
Filming under water raised all sorts of problems for the Life team.
他们在氧气瓶里的气体用完之前
Not least of which was that they were only able to experience
只能短暂体验一下这个水下世界
the underwater world for as long as the air on their backs or in their lungs held out.
但三年来，制作组非常有幸地拍下了
But over three years the team were lucky enough to capture on film
一些鱼类非同寻常的精彩瞬间
some extraordinary moments in the lives of fish.
墨西哥尤卡坦半岛海域
The waters off the Yucatan Peninsula in Mexico
是旗鱼富饶的猎食场所
are a rich hunting ground for Sailfish.
摄影师Rick Rosenthal
Cameraman Rick Rosenthal
和海钓队长Anthony Mendillo合作
has teamed up with sport fishing Captain Anthony Mendillo
试图拍下这些奇异生物的猎食场面
to try and film the hunting behaviour of these amazing animals.
鱼来了！
It's fish!
食鱼鸟带领他们找到了旗鱼
Feeding birds lead them to the sailfish.
在这儿，在这儿呢
Right here.Right here.
在它们的宴会结束前，快速赶到并且下水
Getting to the bait balls and into the water quickly is key,
是非常关键的
before the feast is consumed.
准备
Get ready.
都抓紧了！
Everybody hang on.
我们下水吧，下，下
Let's go swimming, now, now.
去那里
Go on get in there.
让Rick赶快是没错的
It's all very well telling Rick to hurry
这群鱼能游出时速60英里以上
but these fish are capable of swimming at over 60 miles an hour.
想跟上它们非常困难
Just keeping up with them is hard enough.
正好进入它们中间是很必要的
Getting right in amongst the action is vital,
但是Rick还必须尽量不要打扰到它们
but Rick has to try to avoid becoming part of it.
体长接近一米，以刀锋一样的速度破水前进
Bills nearly one metre long, scything through the water at break neck speed
是极速竞赛的保证
are guaranteed to get the heart racing.
Rick绷紧神经
But Rick holds his nerve
旗鱼在他面前逐一地干掉一条条的沙丁鱼
as the sailfish pick off sardine after sardine right in front of him.
就在这一切开始时，就差不多结束了
Almost as soon as it started, it was all over.
今天这真是一场野性的盛宴
That was a wild feed show out there today.
非常狂野
Really wild.
那里应该有50条旗鱼
Must have been 50 sailfish if there was...
49条吧，非常具有侵略性，极度饥饿，每条都在行动
Or 49, but very aggressive fish, very hungry, everybody on the move
我必须不停地把摄影机转啊，转啊，转啊……
and I had to just keep kicking and kicking and kicking
以便跟上节奏
and kicking and kicking and kicking to keep in the action,
因为不一会儿，沙丁鱼就被吃光了
because after a while the sardine patch was eaten up
只剩下一些残肢碎片，结束了
to just a little sliver and then it was over.
在加勒比海另一边2000英里外
Nearly 2,000 miles away on the other side of the Caribbean
另一小组正在进行另一种拍摄
another crew is taking a slightly different approach.
他们打算拍摄飞鱼
They are trying to film flying fish.
摄制组在拂晓时乘Hog Snapper号渔船出发
The team sets out at dawn on the Hog Snapper, a commercial fishing boat.
这里的条件比墨西哥那边的渔船要糟糕的多
Conditions are in stark contrast to the gleaming sport fishing boat in Mexico.
这是Doug，他准备好了，看
There's Doug he's ready for action, look.
他们希望借助本地人的经验，将他们适时地带到合适的地点
They are hoping to use a local fisherman's expertise to put them in the right place at the right time.
是，收到，你们那里有食物
Yeah, Roger that. All you catching there's food.
晚餐、午餐和早餐
You catching dinner, lunch and breakfast.
这只船不大，组员的卧室现在成了厨房
It's not a big boat and the crew's bedroom has now become the kitchen.
今天早餐你们吃煎咸肉和煎鸡蛋
We're having fried bacon and fried egg this morning.
煎咸肉和煎鸡蛋
Fried bacon and fried eggs.
我受过厨师训练……
I'm the trainee chef and I don't...
所以我不必要穿白色雨靴
So I don't get to wear the white wellies.
与其在海面上到处追寻它们
Rather than racing around the ocean chasing the action,
飞鱼摄制组干脆
the flying fish team have to sit it out
坐等飞鱼来找他们
and wait for the fish to come to them.
飞鱼在水里是分散生活的
Flying fish will spawn onto debris in the water
组员们绑了根棕榈叶在船后
and the team tie on to a floating palm frond
确保飞鱼们会聚集着跟过来
to try and make sure they're close by in case the action begins.
果然，他们没等太久
And sure enough, they don't have long to wait.
水面下聚集了成千上万条飞鱼
Thousands of fish have massed below the surface,
它们都在追逐棕榈叶
all intent on reaching the frond.
飞鱼们并不只是将卵排到棕榈叶上
And the frond is not the only thing
（还弄到摄影师身上）
that they're trying to lay their eggs on.
鱼卵的重量将叶子压沉
The weight of the eggs sinks the palm frond
然后产卵结束，拍摄工作也结束了
and puts an end to the spawning and to the crew's filming.
好了，看起来这就是我们想要的
Well, it's moments like that we do the job for.
一切顺利
Everything was right.
光线好，蓝色的水
The light was right, blue water,
四吨多的飞鱼都发狂了
the four tonnes of flying fish all going mental.
多谢，Barry     别客气
Thanks, Barry.You're welcome.
但现在，飞鱼的注意力转向了更大的家伙
But now the fish's attention is turned to something bigger.
它们直接朝船上排卵
Their spawning directly onto the boat.
Barry很担心，提起了一大片鱼卵
Barry is worried as he drags up a huge sheet of eggs.
得把它弄起来，查看一下
Gotta bring it on the boat and check it out.
我五分钟前已经把这个清理干净了，对吧
I cleaned this off like five minutes a go. Right?
现在的问题是，这里的飞鱼太多了
Right now the problem is this, there's too many flying fish...
太多了，我们周围
Too many...around us.
如果我们在这里抛锚过夜，灯开着
If we moor through the nights with the lights on and stuff,
会引来越来越多的飞鱼，它们会将卵排在船体上
more and more will keep coming and what they're doing is they're actually laying on the boat now,
就是说船将成为它们的目标，这可不妙
so the boat has become their object and that is not good.
简单的说，你是在担心，如果我们呆在这里
So basically you're worried that if we just stay on this drift
船可能会沉
we're gonna sink the boat.
五小时后，是的，船后面会增重3000磅
Five hours from now that'll 3,000 pounds.Yeah, yeah.
这会把船弄沉的
In the back here, it will sink the boat.
好的，我们得离开这里
OK, so we've got to leave this area.
是的，此地不宜久留
Yeah, we can't stay here.
仅仅五分钟，就产了这么多卵
Just five minutes of spawning has produced this.
制作组没得选择，只能撤
The team have no option but to move on.
接着的一天，得又一次地寻找飞鱼
The next day the search for flying fish begins all over again.
这一次，制作组想拍摄飞鱼们最有名的行为
This time the team want to film the fish doing what they're famous for.
我们已经拍到了它们产卵的精彩画面
We've got some lovely shots from the spawning
现在，真正的难点是让它们飞起来
but now the really hard bit of trying to get them flying.
将会是很好的挑战
Gonna be, gonna be a good challenge.
鱼就在周围，但对拍摄来说太远了
The fish are around, but they're all too far off to film.
它们今早的行为令人印象深刻
The action is impressive this morning,
捉摸不定，很难忘，但是太远了
unpredictable but impressive but it's distant,
并不在船附近
it's not happening next to the boat today.
它们要么是被追赶，要么是随意的，看！
They're either being chased off or they're just not interested. Look!
看，都跳起来了
Look, look! Ah it's loads.
Ay, ay, ay!
接下来一天，组员们决定用别的方法
The next day the crew decides to try a different approach.
好了，我们走吧
All right, lets go.
现在他们到了目的地
Now they're just where they need to be,
但正好处在了火线上
but it puts them directly in the firing line.
我猜是这只
I guess that's one!
尽管被撞到，他们的策略是值得的
Despite being bombarded, their strategy is paying off.
太奇妙了，我们在小船上呆了很长时间
That was amazing, we spent a long time in that wee boat today. Thanks.
最后的两小时，我们都累了
But the last two hours were just off the scale.
我们被一次又一次地撞上
We were just getting shot after shot. We need...
等不及去大的监视器上观看，但感觉好极了
Can't wait to watch it on the big monitor but it felt really good.
Doug说的对
And Doug is right,
成功了
it worked.
飞鱼飞到了空中
Flying fish taking to the air and flying.
放慢40倍
Slowed down 40 times.
通过和经常捕鱼的人合作
By working with people more used to catching fish than filming them
Life制作组能以一个独特的视角
the Life team have been able to gain a unique insight
探知鱼类的隐秘世界
into the hidden world of fish.
生命进化史函授海报上的免费电话
For your free Open University Tree of Life poster call...
或登陆我们的网站
..or visit the website.